Character is complex.
And I would always challenge my students.
I would say, push them to the wall.
Push them to the wall.
And that's where the drama of being alive is.
Can you live with yourself if you
have to do something that you ordinarily would hate to do?
But the circumstance makes it necessary for you.
So you got person against themselves,
person against person.
Is that it?
No.
There's a third level of drama.
Tell me about these relationships
with characters.
So if character drives drama and voice drives character,
what drives voice?
And this might be lesson number one of craft.
So when you're writing, what are you
doing to make it feel alive?
Read the first sentence again, because you'll
see a little registral trick there.
Tell me when to stop.
Each child's tree has its own excellence.
Stop.
Richard Powers won the Pulitzer Prize
for The Overstory in 2000.
And next year, his place runs for four worldwide.
Or the Bestclockwise.
By the way, can you believe it?
I raised my hand.
My vaiila.
I got a little bit redirected.
But the thing about reading narrative is that it's
about showing that you're not alone,
and you're actually moving forward.
And we learned this from our work.
Hi.
I want to show you how drama, conflict, voice, and dialogue
can bring a character to life.
So if you're somebody who's trying to write better stories
and write with more life in your own work,
well, you're going to love this conversation
with Richard Powers.
Character is complex,
and we all do this in the course of our lives.
You know, our brains have adapted
to try to understand the hidden motivations of other people.
In fact, when you talk to evolutionary biologists,
there will be some who say,
we needed the big brain because we were social.
You know, we had...
I mean, mammals have, by and large,
solved a lot of the problems of predation,
of avoiding prey, you know,
responding flexibly to change.
You know,
you can get by on a lot less hardware,
but what you need a lot of hardware for
is keeping track of who's up and who's down,
who's in and who's out,
who owes a favor.
All the interactions.
That's right. That's right.
So we're all novelists in our own lives.
We're all saying,
I...
This guy is remembering
what happened between us
20 years ago.
Right.
And he's holding a grudge,
or I haven't seen her in a long time.
I wonder if she's...
I wonder if she's also a little bit nostalgic
about the road that we did not take.
You know, all those kinds of things
that we do with each other all the time.
Those are the underlying skills
that we use to assemble character
when we're creating stories.
Hmm.
Who's a character in a recent novel
that you still feel like
you have a really intimate relationship with?
Well, I'm very close
to the people in Playground City.
I'm close to the people in Playground still.
And one of the great joys
of being a novelist
is you get up in the morning and you say,
how are they going to surprise me today?
One of the great sadnesses of a novelist
is you have to come to an end
and you have to surrender the manuscript
at some point,
and it becomes this fixed thing.
And yet your heart is still saying,
did I do right by them?
Hmm.
Was there something else that they wanted or needed
that I didn't get to?
So, you know, there's an odd way
in which the character lives on
in your sense of potential or prospect
as you're telling stories.
But, you know, the two central protagonists
in this book,
Todd Keen,
who is a Northside Chicagoan,
white, privileged, wealthy,
and Rafael,
young black guy from the Southside
who's coming from a very different socioeconomic stratum
and whose personal history is very different than Todd's,
in weird ways,
I used them both as alter egos.
Mm.
You know, I used them almost psychoanalytically
to get to various things in my personal past
that I wanted still to work through
here at the age of 67.
I put them in colloquial terms.
I put them in a way that I could
say that they were in a collision with each other.
Character leads naturally into drama
in a way that we can talk about.
But I let them collide.
You know, they formed a friendship
that was tight, dedicated,
but also highly competitive
and with a certain degree of wariness and distrust,
a certain degree of ribbing
and crap shoveling,
as males do to each other.
Um...
And the drama that arose out of that
was naturally a kind of extension
of all the unfinished drama of my young life,
you know, from the age of 10 to the age of 30
and beyond.
Character leads into drama.
I think that's true.
I mean, when we think of character,
you know, I used to teach character
using something like the Stanislavski method.
I don't know if you've had writers
who have approached it that way,
but he was a great theoretician of acting
and how to...
An actor prepares, it's one of his works,
and, you know, how to inhabit a role
of someone on stage who isn't you.
And how to locate in the world
that role
something in the core inner values of that character
that you yourself can identify with.
Mm.
Knowing full well that you don't...
You are not that person.
You do not belong to that world.
But somehow abstracting it enough
so that you can use your own inner experiences
and core inner values
to inhabit and participate in that other character's...
And of course, what an actor does to inhabit a role
is not that different than what a novelist has to do
to create a character.
So, make this concrete for me.
I don't know why I was thinking of Nemo.
And Nemo is, you know, this little kid fish,
and Nemo wants to get out... Right.
...and go do things, go explore the ocean.
And then you have, what's his name, Marlin, the dad?
Marlin, I think, is his name.
Marlin is this super overprotective dad. Right.
And Marlin has done very early on,
and he's done very early in the movie,
he's like, are you sure you want to go to school today?
Because it's the first day of school.
And he's trying to say, stay home, stay home,
because he is this just gripping on the life of his young son.
So, if we take that, tell me about what you're saying
through the prism of those characters.
So, I used to do this.
And this also derives from the Stanislavski method,
but I used to teach characterization as an onion.
So, you have...
On the outside of a person,
I don't necessarily mean the outside
in the way that they perform themselves in the world,
because that's always a delicate and elaborate dance,
hiding a lot of things, displaying a lot of things,
you know, negotiating a lot of things.
But in terms of the psychic economy of that character,
in the outer shell are the traits.
And he's got a green shirt on,
it's got a little insignia,
a nice haircut,
you know, he holds one hand...
You know, all the things that you can use
to make a character visual and visible to the reader.
But those traits come from somewhere, right?
They derive from things that are farther in the interior of the onion.
And beneath that level of surface,
you know, physical traits or behavioral traits,
you might have mannerisms.
Like, he likes to unnerve people.
Whenever somebody says something,
instead of saying,
no, right, he'll say,
what do you mean by that?
And that mannerism of challenging or subverting
or undercutting somebody...
Man, there's a sensitivity of awareness
that you must have.
You must really have to have.
And is that something that you're cultivating?
I think it can be cultivated,
because I don't think I ever came by any of this naturally.
You know, if you're talking about,
you know, various distribution curves of people,
some of whom have very high emotional intelligence,
are immediately aligned with reading other people.
And then other people,
you know, the cliché is the other end of the spectrum
are people who do better with machines
or mathematical concepts.
I'm probably on that side of that spectrum.
But I do think we can all,
we are all conversant,
you know, to some degree,
with finding, you know, equivalents and analogs
across the ways of knowing the world.
So the next level inside of mannerisms
would be what I call core inner values.
And I get this again from people
who have done a lot of thinking,
about the creation and inhabiting of characters.
So, but by,
a value has to be something like honesty,
or fidelity,
or perseverance, right?
So we're now seeing,
oh, the reason he holds his hand like that
is he has a manner,
where he wants to set other people at ease.
And underneath that manner
of wanting to set people at ease
is the value of complicity,
or attentiveness,
or, you know, whatever it is.
But you see how multiple values
can drive the same mannerism.
Multiple mannerisms can be,
can lie behind the same trait.
So you have to find,
you have to find ways of making coherence
so that the outward behavior of the person
is both hiding
and revealing things that they need,
things that they want to preserve in the world.
And I would always challenge my students,
I would say,
push them to the wall.
Push them to the wall.
Yeah, so I'd say,
you know this guy is a good guy.
You know he values honesty,
but you know he also values fidelity.
Now, put him in a place
where he cannot have both.
Mm-hmm.
So now you've got to make a choice.
Yes.
What is your core inner value?
And what one will fall by the wayside
when push comes to shove
because you've got to choose?
Right.
I mean, the scenarios are obvious.
You know, your friend has just done something wrong.
Do you go to him and say,
look, man, you've got to pay for that.
You have to own up to that.
Or do you say, I'm a good, faithful friend.
I, you know, I'm just going to do what I want.
I'm going to do what I want.
You know, I'm just going to support this guy.
I'll be with you no matter what.
Yeah.
That's a story.
In fact, that's 10,000 stories.
Yeah.
Right?
So what I'm hearing you say is,
you take these two values,
and you take them to the extreme.
You almost make somebody fight those two values internally.
Yeah.
What would it take?
What situation or challenge would it take
to force that person to have to jump ship from one
and embrace the other?
Now, that's drama.
Yeah.
And that's a very specific kind of drama.
It's interior drama.
And in the hierarchy of drama that I learned way back
in grade school, back in the day,
using very sexist language, that would be called
a man versus himself.
OK?
And that fundamental kind of interior instability,
you know, when I go out into the tumult of the world,
my sense of self has to readjust.
My sense of what I think was most important to me has to change.
Mm-hmm.
That's the classic psychological novel.
How do we cope with the differences in the dramas inside our own head?
Because look, you know, I don't want to have to choose
between honesty and fidelity.
I want to have both.
Well, life doesn't always let you have both.
Right.
And that's where the drama of being alive is.
Can you live with yourself if you have to do something?
If you have to do something that you ordinarily would hate to do,
but the circumstance makes it necessary for you?
Yes.
Now, I'm doing that, and David's doing that too.
And here we are sitting in the same room, right?
And you need something from me, and I need something from you.
Right?
You have core inner value that's very different than my core inner value.
So November's coming up.
Let's say for point of argument that my core inner value is equality,
and your core inner value is freedom.
And now we have to go to the election box,
and we have to vote for one candidate.
Mm-hmm.
I can't believe what you're voting for.
You see what I'm saying?
Now we have interpersonal drama.
Now we have the sociological novel or the political novel
where I can make you completely sympathetic to the reader.
Mm-hmm.
And...
I can make myself completely sympathetic to the reader.
But now the reader's watching two people collide
in a way where they, the reader, has to say who's right.
The author doesn't necessarily have to say who's right,
but the reader has to say,
if that were me...
Which would I do?
How would I jump?
I got to jump.
Got to jump.
Got to put a vote in the ballot box.
So you got person against themselves,
person against person.
Right.
Is that it?
No.
There's a third level of drama,
which is that human beings
want to have a certain story in the world.
They want to have a project.
They want to have...
They have a conception
of what a good life is
and how we can best go about doing that on this Earth.
The rest of the world,
and it is a very large rest of the world,
a very big, comprehensive and interconnected living planet,
might be hostile to that idea of what it is that we want most.
It might be at best indifferent to it,
or it might be very sympathetic to it.
But there is a battle between humans in the aggregate
and a world of which humans are only a very tiny part.
Mm-hmm.
And that level you would call man against the elements
or man against the universe.
Or man against life.
So you have the psychological component of all stories.
You have the sociological or political element of all stories.
But you also have this environmental
or metaphysical element to all stories.
Mm-hmm.
Now, if I...
You know, when I was reading everything I could get my hands on
and deciding that I was going to give my life
to this craft and this work,
and I was reading especially contemporary novels
in the 80s and in the 90s
and even into the early 2000s,
there were a lot, a lot of novels
that were exceptionally good at psychology
and very, very good at sociology and politics,
but almost never ventured beyond the human world.
Mm.
Almost never introduced the idea
that what we want out of our lives on this planet
might not be commensurate with what the planet wants.
So the whole third kind of drama
was disappearing from literary fiction.
We were getting extremely able and capable
in our ability to tell stories about humans,
but only as if humans were autonomous
and inter... independent from everything else.
Right.
And it seemed to me that can't be right.
And I started to look at the history of literary fiction
and then the history of world literature
even before the novel.
And I was looking for that third kind of story.
And I saw, I mean, you can think of great examples of it, right?
I mean, if I said, tell me a book about man versus nature
or man versus, you know, the gods
or man versus the elements.
Greek mythology, a bunch.
All of it.
Almost all mythological traditions.
Now, bring it up to the present.
What do you think, you know,
what's the latest kind of great book in the American canon
that you think really concerned,
took seriously the idea of man versus nature?
I have no idea.
I don't know.
You gotta go back a ways.
Yeah.
And you gotta go back to Moby Dick
or you gotta go back to the frontier,
American frontier novel.
It's been that long, huh?
Well, I mean, there are always exceptions.
Sure.
Right?
But there's a dip.
There's a real dip where, you know,
from 1851 when Moby Dick's published
to, you know, 1914,
the start of the First World War,
you see a trend for sure
where that novel starts to seem quaint,
like the battle against nature.
You know, it's like Jack London, you know,
it's well, you know,
why doesn't it seem literary to us?
Because I think the practitioners of storytelling
were under the mistaken impression
that man had defeated nature,
that human beings had won that drama.
And now we could invoke that drama,
we could invoke that drama kind of nostalgically,
but it wasn't a real issue in our lives anymore.
Our technologies had gotten so powerful
that it didn't seem like questions
that we had to ask anymore.
Now, what happens in the last couple decades
is there's a growing awareness
that we didn't win that war.
In fact, we're losing that war.
And we're in bad shape,
not just on the climate front,
but on the species extinction front.
Yeah.
And now that drama comes flooding back
into the literary novel.
It never left the novel of science fiction.
It never left fantasy.
I mean, fantasy is man against nature, right?
It's telling that those things became second class,
those genres became subordinate genres
in the eyes of the people who wanted
to be practitioners of literary fiction, right?
But now, where it would have been strange for me in 1980
to pick up a new literary fiction
that had a lot of non-human elements in it,
non-human agents or non-human concerns
or taking place seriously
or taking other kinds of creatures seriously,
now it's rare to pick one up
that isn't addressing this question
of how are we going to stay here much longer.
As you were thinking about the overstory
and learning about trees
and developing a kind of empathy for trees, right?
I think of how big is the distance
between you as the person
and the, dare I say, consciousness of a tree.
It almost felt like your mind
and the consciousness of trees fused together.
And I know that in your research process,
you just spent a lot of time in the woods.
And I would love to hear about that research,
but even more fundamentally,
how you developed that kind of empathy
for trees and turning up the dial
of just how real they were to you.
I found that in old literature.
You mentioned mythology, indigenous stories.
And of course, I found it also
by recovering my own earliest sense of narrative.
So, you know, I've often said that young children
are animists, you know,
or, you know, they have,
they take seriously these magical creatures around us.
You know, I just looked at some crows flying past
and looking at these marvelous locusts out of the window,
you know, and a child could look at that
and know that that creature,
that creature is alive in really profound ways
that adults now stop taking seriously.
No, it's just wood. It's just wood.
Right.
So to go back to my own childhood pantheism
and to go back to the stories
that underwrite oral literature
that know that you can't talk about human beings,
you can't understand human beings,
except in conversation with the neighbors,
you know, with understanding them
in the full context of who we're not.
You know, and our fascination with the nonhuman world
is that somehow we can see qualities
in these other ways of being in the world
that resonate with our own values.
So to look at the nonhuman world
is also to understand interior drama.
Mm-hmm.
So it's not just a question of giving trees voice.
It's a question of remembering those voices
inside human beings that were suppressed
by this cultural colonialism that said,
no, no, no, don't, you know,
pay no attention to the world behind you.
It's behind the curtain.
It's just us.
So to recover, to recover that amazement
wasn't a separate thing than, you know,
than to go deep into character.
For me, for the creation of that book,
they became the same enterprise.
Well, what's wild about the overstory
is how articulate you are about trees.
Let me just read this.
We found that trees could communicate
over the air and through their roots.
Common sense hooted us down.
We found that trees take care of each other.
Collective science dismissed the ideas.
Outsiders discovered how seeds remember
the seasons of their childhood
and set buds accordingly.
Outsiders discovered that trees sense
the presence of other nearby life,
that a tree learns to save water,
that trees feed their young and synchronize their masts,
and bank resources and warm kin
and send out signals to wasps
to come and save them from attacks.
I mean, Richard, for somebody who didn't know
a lot about trees before he started writing
this book, to then getting to a place
where you could see that, feel that,
put that into language, and then do it
lyrically and poetically,
it's just astonishing.
And I just need to understand
how you did that.
Well, my whole project from the beginning
has been driven forward by these ways
of knowing the world that we think
are incompatible or inimical.
You know, we're not all incompatible.
We're incompatible in the sense that
we're incompatible in the sense that
we're, you know, opposite
or in opposition to each other.
The way of knowing the world
through empiricism and science
and the way of knowing the world
through intuition and the spirit,
I think the greatest science writers
know that these aren't really
combating programs,
that they actually are commensal,
that they actually depend on one another.
So, you know,
I think that's the way
that we're going to be
in the future.
So, in the passage that you read,
this character Patricia Westerford,
she's an outsider,
and she's not afraid to anthropomorphize,
which drives a lot of scientists nuts
even now, although there are interesting
ways in which that attitude is changing
because it has prevented us from
seeing certain things about
the world beyond us.
But she uses a vocabulary
that's very lyrical and very poetic,
very spiritual,
and it's a very powerful
way of thinking about
the world beyond us.
And so, in the passage that you read,
has some kind of empirical backing
in peer-reviewed journal articles
that I researched when I was reading the book.
So, to me, that's going to be our salvation.
We have to know the world
the way a scientist knows the world,
and we have to know the world
the way an animist or pantheist child
knows the world.
And if we can get those both going
in our individual selves
we can be sure that we're
going to be able to
move forward in our own lives.
And I think that this is...
So, I didn't grow up
liking novels very much.
I didn't read novels.
It just wasn't super compelling to me.
And reading this now,
it's something about reading it out loud
is really showing me
what the novel can uniquely do.
I'll read a little bit more.
A forest knows things.
They wire themselves up underground.
Human brains aren't shaped to see.
Root plasticity solving problems
and making decisions.
Fungal synapses.
What else do you want to call it?
Link enough trees together
and a forest grows where?
And, I mean, it almost brings tears to my eyes.
And what it's doing is
that language is
giving life to something
that I've seen 10,000 times.
And like you were saying earlier,
you just become an adult.
You're like, ah, it's just a chunk of wood and some leaves.
And you're giving them life
and vitality again through the language.
And that's the great grace
of the form, the novel form.
You could have come across those facts
in a very well done
popularization of the new forestry
and, you know,
all the discoveries about
symbiotic relationships
in a forest that have come
over the last several decades.
And you could have grasped them intellectually.
But I think
as psychologists,
as psychologists know,
the apprehension
of fact
and
a shift
in values
are not the same thing.
And that we can be
seduced
much more
by emotion and affect
and feeling
than we can by statistics
and graphs and arguments.
In fact,
emotion is interesting
etymologically.
So it means to move,
to move someone.
You know,
to move through
something.
And this has been
verified again in so many
laboratories using so many
experiments.
But the smallest
appeal to affect
and to identification
can make
people do things
that argument cannot.
There's odd
experiments that make you wonder
how fragile
and labile mankind is.
Like,
they'll have subjects
reading two different
texts or three different texts
with control text and a
text about, you know,
a story about someone who does something
good for someone else.
And ostensibly the experiment
is about comprehension.
So someone reads some data
and someone reads a control
neutral narrative
that has no bearing on, you know,
the question of emotion.
And someone reads a fictional passage
that, you know,
has the potential to
move you.
To break your heart, to make you cry a little bit.
And the ostensible
experiment is we want to test your reading comprehension.
Please answer the following questions.
So all three groups answer the following questions.
And when you're done
answering the questions, you know,
please take your exams down the hall
and deposit them at this door.
And meanwhile,
a confederate is walking down the hall
in the other direction and they dump their
pencils on the ground as if by accident.
You know, they've got a bunch of
they're carrying
a bunch of goods and they
make a mess.
The group that has read
the story
is
far more likely to stop and help
the person who just
dumped their goods all over the hallway.
And it
doesn't really have that much to do
with, you know,
with the temperaments of the individuals in that group.
They've all been baseline shifted
for a moment anyway
to be more empathetic,
to identify more with this person who's
now in a moment of suffering.
And that's what fiction does.
It invites
identification. It invites
you to say, who would I be
if I weren't myself but that guy?
And simply
the act of doing that
increases your desire
to be connected,
to be empathetic,
to be helpful to another person.
Hey, I want to tell you about a new
site that I built called Writing Examples.
We take writers like
Steinbeck, Orwell,
Seinfeld, and break down what
makes their writing so good.
If that sounds like it's kind of your
thing, well go to writingexamples.com.
And if you go there,
you enter your email, I'll send you my
three favorite editions right away.
Alright, back to the episode.
As I was reading
that, I started,
I really felt how
attentive you are to rhythm and pacing
and language and the different
hues of a paragraph.
And I'm curious how
you think about sentences and
the way you write
in order to create that effect in the reader.
Yeah, so when you think about
a good book, a good novel,
there are a lot
of dogs pulling
the sled, you know, there are a lot of
horses in harness. And some are,
some of the concerns of
crafting a novel are
what I would call low level or very,
very granular.
Diction,
register, syntax.
And then, you know,
you work up to the kinds of things
that you're talking about, sentence level, pace,
and cadence. And then the
scene grows out of that. And how long
should the scene be and what is the
flow and the shape of the scene? What is
the tempo of the scene? And those
emerge out of the layers
underneath.
So you have a language as one
way of, you know, as one of the
dogs in the
pulling sled. And you have
drama and you have
character. And you have
form and you have structure. And
different readers attach
themselves more happily or more
easily to different elements of fiction.
Right. You know, like,
people can come right out and say,
I'm a character guy,
you know, I just want to see if these people
feel robust and vital and
three-dimensional, you know. And
the story,
yeah, I'll read for plot,
but it's basically,
do I know this person, you know,
can I recognize myself in this person?
And there were other
people, and for a long time I was in this
category, I didn't
care about characterization, I didn't care about
plot, I didn't care, I just
wanted beautiful language.
That's how I am. Isn't that funny?
You know, because
identification with character is the dominant
way of consuming a novel now,
in this culture, at this moment,
people can look at us
and cite that fact
as if it's a little freakish or a
little offbeat. I like that and
descriptiveness. Yeah, because
setting a scene, you know,
even before there are
human agents or non-human agents in that
scene, for me, can
be, you know,
some of the most glorious kinds of fictional
experiences you can have. Whereas, if you
go to an MFA program,
you're likely to hear people say things like
show, don't tell, which means
don't spend a lot of time setting the
scene, just get people in there doing things.
So something is lost
when you privilege one aspect
of a fictional experience over all the others.
I think the
ideal strategy
is getting all those elements
pulling in the same direction
and feeding
on one another. So
the question is, we talked about
how drama grows
out of character. Well, character
grows out of voice.
To a large extent,
we come to know the people
on the page
by how they're explaining themselves.
Sure. And how they're performing
themselves for other people.
And what they're asking from other people.
So,
the moment you hear somebody,
you start to hear somebody, you can also start to
see that person. Forrest Gump
from a movie is
a great example of just
the way he speaks and
the simplicity of his language
is a place where voice
really then leads to character.
Yeah. So if
if
character drives drama
and voice drives character,
what drives voice?
And the answer is
you're starting to get down to the nuts and bolts of your
tool chest, which is
the words,
the individual words, and the way
they are
aligned in a sentence.
Right? So
I'll do the first one first,
although typically I would try
with my students,
I did it different ways in different years, but
I would show the inseparability
of these things. I'd show the questions
of register and diction
are also the questions of syntax
and cadence and pacing. But
the easy ones, the lowest
level,
is what is the
register of that word
and, you know, what does
that word mean? And to answer
those questions is far from
trivial. When you say the register
of a word, what do you mean by that?
So, linguists will talk about
the levels
of speech that people
use. And
sometimes you'll see three.
Casual in the middle,
formal above it, and
you know, down and dirty, you know,
slangy
at the bottom. Sure, yeah.
And sometimes
you'll see four. You know, you'll see different
approaches to answering this question of
how register works.
But when you think of the various ways
that you can say,
hand me that. Right.
Give me that. Yeah. Hey, will you please
pass that? Yeah. Completely different. Yeah.
And there are a dozen more.
I mean, there's no end, actually, to the ways that
you can say that. Yeah. I mean, you can
literally just say, yo, and then
point at it. That's correct.
And you are
performing a submit. You're
requesting something specific that can
be identified, but you're also
sending signals beyond signals
about who you are, about
who you think the other person is,
about the kinds of values that
you want to manifest to the other person,
about the kinds of values that you want to
encourage or suppress in the other person.
All of those come out of voice.
And voice, again, is
what words, what,
how formal or
informal are you
going for in terms of your word
choice? It would often
be eye-opening to my students when I
would come into class and I'd say, you know,
because you're speakers of
English, you
have a kind of built-in
bilingualism.
And they'd say, what do you mean by that?
I'd say,
for historical reasons,
you have the possibility
of drawing
on two completely
different histories
and origins of words
in order to create
registral and color effects.
Are you talking about Latin and Anglo-Saxon?
Absolutely.
So, if
you say I live in a mansion,
right, or if you say
I live in a house,
why does one sound more expensive than
the other? I mean, back
all the way at the beginning, they were the same
thing. Maison and, you know, our
English house were the same thing.
But, you know, because
the Normans came over
to England and conquered the
local English people
and set themselves up in court
the
Latinate through French
words
got a higher socioeconomic register.
Ha ha, right.
And so immediately
the words you use
talk about your class.
And
when my students would make
this realization, it was like, wow,
I've got some power that I didn't have
before. Maybe I could hear it
in my ear when somebody's
being snooty or somebody's
trying to establish their street cred.
But now that I know
the
actual rules for making that work,
my ear becomes better.
Right? And
the difference
between freedom
and liberty
becomes more audible.
Right. Right?
So that's
the word level considerations for
voice. The other
consideration is
the sentence level.
So, and I would try
to teach this. It's a very
complicated question because
English grammar is not trivial
and, but it's immensely flexible.
And you can create all kinds
of different palette effects and color effects
by
by using
the flexible
syntax and grammar of English.
But I would say
how can I teach to my students
where they don't have to go back
to this subject that they hated when they were
in sixth grade, but they could
get the meat and potatoes of it.
And I was thinking, can I do
80% of the work
with 80% of the effect with 20%
of the grammar, you know? Sure.
And so I boil it down to saying
think about
sentences as belonging
basically to one of three classes.
So
the heart and soul of sentence, call it
predication, is the main
subject and the main verb.
Every sentence has
these. Now you might have
an implied main subject
and maybe an imperative
verb where, you know,
give me that would be an example, right?
Give, the predication
is you give me that.
So the subject drops away
and you just have the command.
But every
sentence is built around
that kernel.
If you can find on the page
or in your ear that
kernel, then you
can build the sentence in the way
that allows the sentence
to recreate
emotionally,
prosodically,
the mental state
that the speaker is in, or
that the narrator wants you to
be in, in that the
sentence starts to participate
in the affect of the thing
that it's describing, right?
So if I start
with my predication
and I put in a lot of
other modifiers, that
creates a certain kind of syntax.
He pointed
the gun at his friend,
right? There's
a kind of front-loaded shock
to that, right?
Or the gun exploded
and
a whiff
of smoke exited
the barrel, you know. These are clauses
that have the
action up front, you know, the
main subject, main verb get delivered like that,
and then we see the consequences of those things.
Now, that's a very different
thing than delaying the predication
after a lot of
modifiers. So if you want
to put the reader into an entirely
opposite mental state,
you could say,
way back
across the yard,
near the fence,
where a tiny brook
ran along
an old hedgerow
she hid.
Right?
And of course,
by having these modifiers
first the reader is in this suspenseful state.
Yeah, it's like, what are you going to say? What are you going to say?
And
she doesn't appear until the very end.
So she is hidden from the reader
in the sentence. Oh, wow,
I did not catch that. Right? Yeah.
In the same way that she's hidden
in the physical spin. Ha ha ha,
I did not catch that. You have to wait for it, wait for it.
There she is.
Right? Now the third way would be to split
that predication down the middle and basically
start with your subject
and put a bunch of stuff in the middle
and then a verb, you know.
And you can do
this for all kinds of reasons too. You can create suspense
with that, you can create comedy
with it, right?
It's probably the rarest
form. If you count the sentences
in an average novel, most of them
are going to be in the first
species, you know, where the
subject and verb are pretty up front.
A smaller
number are going to be this delayed predication
and maybe the smallest.
I don't know, I'd like to do that experiment
sometime and actually get the data.
But my intuition is that splitting
the predication is the rarest,
but it has a very powerful
and, you know, not only
the effect in itself can create
these different forms of delay or suspense
or intrigue,
but using it
inside a paragraph when you've just
had three sentences
of, you know,
trailing sentence in a row,
suddenly stopping and changing
that, changing it up, it's like a key change
in music or going to a different chord.
Right. Tell me about
writing descriptively because
it's the kind of thing
that people try to do and
then all of a sudden they sound like they're trying too
hard. And I want to read this sentence
because I think it's a good example of
how you write descriptively.
And I want to hear how you think
about doing this. You write,
Each child's tree has its own
excellence. The ash diamond
shaped bark, the walnuts
long compound leaves,
the maples shower
of helicopters, the vase-like
spread of elm, the ironwoods
fluted muscle.
What's cool about that is I can see it, I can see it,
I can see it, I can see it. You're almost
cutting between
different scenes. But I
find that whenever I try to do that,
the writing just sounds overdone.
It's like, David, why are you trying so hard?
Well, it's okay.
It's okay to try hard because you always have an
edit where you can make it look
more effortless.
And, you know, to
push yourself
in composition and say,
let me make a note to myself about the
kinds of effects that I'm
going after.
Maybe they're too obvious.
Maybe, you know, maybe they're too blocked out.
But at least you know now
what effects it is
that you're after. So think about that first draft
as a note to yourself about,
you know, about the psychic
state that you want your sentence, your descriptions
to participate in. Now when you go back,
you can hide your footwork.
And you can make it more elegant.
You can take out the ones, the notes
that are a bit too loud or that
announce too clearly what your intentions
are. But in that passage,
you know, one of the tricks is that
the idea
in that passage is to make each
species of tree vivid and distinct.
To give them characteristics
that are different from all the other
trees. But to do
it, I'm
introducing, it's almost like
going back to Patricia Westerford
and saying, there's subtle
little elements of anthropomorphism
in that sentence or pantheism
or animism in those descriptions.
The ironwood's fluted muscle.
Yeah. And now
it's like that
trunk that's so visually distinct
in that tree
now becomes like a weightless tree.
You see it flexing and you can
see the sinews.
So it's a subtle invitation
to elicit
the animism in the reader.
Oh yeah, I've looked at a tree
and I've thought
that tree is evil
or that tree is
shy or that, you know,
all these projected emotions.
Majestic. Right. Yeah.
But read the first sentence again because
you'll see a little registral trick there too.
Okay, tell me when to stop.
Each child's tree has its own
excellence. Stop.
Were you
expecting that word as the final
word of that clause? No.
It's like
a great
song where
you hear the phrase
and you think you know the way the chords are going
and then all of a sudden
at the end of that phrase
you hear a sudden and interesting
change of color or change of
instrumentation or change of pitch.
The last thing you would
think to apply to a tree
would be some degree of excellence.
Now
I always think, you know,
the beginning
of a sentence and the end of a sentence
are very powerful places
to set a reader's
expectation and then to surprise
the reader's expectation.
Each child's tree has its own
degree of excellence.
Right?
And the reader's unconscious.
Just reading along for the music of it
and the color of it and the images
being created.
But the composer
is saying
that word raises
the tension a little bit
at the end of that sentence.
And it's not
the one that the...
As we read along we're constantly saying
what's coming next, what's coming next.
We're like an AI.
Right.
We're like a most likely word.
We're like a large language model.
We have a model of the world.
And as I add each new word
to this sentence
you are deciding
which way I'm going to
spin.
Exactly.
You got to...
You can play off that expectation.
You can set it in motion
and then say, nope, this way, that way.
So how is it different, say,
when you're describing a person.
But then you write,
The farm was where Nick first started sketching.
The pencil dreams of boys.
Rockets, outlandish cars,
massed armies,
imaginary cities, more baroque with detail
each year.
Then wilder textures, directly observed.
The forest of hairs on a caterpillar's back.
And the stormy weather maps
and the grain of floorboards.
Yeah.
And you know it's interesting to read something
that I wrote
now.
Seven or eight years ago.
I'm in a different place.
The world is in a different place.
That book exists and
you know, its trajectory I could never
have foreseen when I was working on it.
And I'm listening to those phrases
on the one hand, the way
a brand new reader is listening to them.
Because enough time has passed for me to
forget what that passage,
how that passage worked.
So I hear that pencil, the pencil dreams of boys.
And I don't know,
it's an odd metaphor for me.
I don't know if I can remember the word
for a second.
And then you get the catalogue of things that boys might sketch
and oh the pencil dreams of boys.
Well what's so cool about this is
I put, it put me back
to being a kid.
I used to design airports in my room when I was a kid.
So this is about rockets and outlandish cars.
It has nothing to do with airplanes.
But something about the similarity put me back
to being an eight year old kid,
kind of messing around and sketching around
and designing baseball this
and football that.
And now that I'm rereading it,
so much of what makes this resonate with me.
Yeah, now you can look at the individual words
and the syntax and say,
what is he doing to put me in that mental state?
Beyond the simple,
literal conveyance of the sentence.
I have to say,
in all honesty,
and this might be lesson number one of craft,
I'm also listening and saying,
no, I would do that differently now.
Give me a red pen.
You know, because that's writing.
You are never going to be able
to get that sentence done with it.
Because you're a moving target,
your reader is a moving target,
the world is a moving target.
You look at that sentence and you say,
give me another shot at that.
So, you know,
when you say you look at your first draft
and it's frustrating for you,
I say that's not a bug,
that's a feature.
Let that frustration be another form
of seeing your desire.
So how many times do you rewrite those sentences?
Oh, gosh.
You know,
when you're processing,
it's hard to say 12 or 14.
It's just continuous.
It just keeps happening.
Never ends.
You know, you wake up the next day
and you're reworking the previous day's material.
And then you get to the end of the weekend
and you've got a chapter and you read the chapter
and you rework the chapter again.
And then the whole book is finished
and now you say it's time to go do a second draft.
Well, that second draft is actually now,
I think, a thousand times or more.
You know, and then you send it off
to your first readers
and they say, eh,
it got a little slow for me
from 140 to 200, you know.
And now you say, well, how do I pick the pace up?
And you go back and you redraft it again.
But all I'm saying is,
accept that as part of the glory
of the process of writing.
Don't fight it as something
you wish you could finally make it.
You know,
you wish you could finally make it
right,
because there's no final right.
You know, I take this book
that was published yesterday,
I go behind the podium tonight,
I start reading from it,
I want to change it.
Wow.
When you get frustrated
when you're writing
and you're agitated or
tense because you're not
getting something right,
what is the nature of the things
that aren't quite right for you?
Well, it could be anything.
It could be deafness, you know, or...
Deafness?
Yeah, like I don't know
what this person's trying to say
or how they should be trying to say it.
It could be a dramatic problem.
Oh, my God, I just realized
that I've been, you know,
I've been counting on these two characters
to be
disagreeing about this matter,
but now that I see them both in context,
I'm not sure they would be.
And I think that's the thing.
So you could, you,
you're constantly having
to course correct.
You're constantly having
to discover the things that your
unconscious knew.
Sometimes you can't discover it.
So the ways of going wrong are infinite.
And the ways of going right
are not final.
So,
ride it, you know.
It's so definitely like surfing.
For me,
the craft
tip here
is relax.
Forgive yourself.
Know,
because it always comes around
to something more satisfying,
that all you need to do
is let it breathe a little bit.
Go out, take a hike, you know,
stand in front
of a tree, you know, breathe
the air, you know, drink the drink.
Relax
the perfectionism that says
I need to get
this in a perfect final state.
Let it, let it be process.
I want to talk about introductions.
Just how you think about
where these books begin.
For Overstore, you write
first there was nothing.
Then there was everything.
For Playground,
before the Earth, before the Moon,
before the stars, before the Sun,
before the sky, even before the sea,
there was only time
and Ta-Aroa.
Why do you choose those? How do you think
about that? You're revealing
something
that I probably had
never consciously articulated
about what I like in
beginnings.
But I see it clearly in
both of these. I want
to situate my
stories in a mythological framework.
Yes. But I
also, you know, I'm imitating a certain
kind of cinematography too.
Like
a
great films that
start with a really distant
wide establishing shot.
Yep.
And then, you know, go to a mid shot
and then go to a close.
In my ear, I want to
say, here is
the size of the canvas.
Now we're going to explore this, but don't
forget that the canvas is all
the way out here.
So if that opening
can be kind of cosmic,
then you earn
the right to tell a local story
and let it germinate
and grow into
the larger
frame that you've set for the story.
But I'll tell you,
I love
opening lines.
I love looking at the books that I
love and seeing how sometimes
the entire book is contained in the
microcosm of the first sentence or
paragraph. All the conflicts,
all the dramas, all the characterization,
you know, are hinted at
in a way that the reader can't possibly
see or
anticipate.
I mean, Romeo and Juliet, two houses
both alike in dignity in
Feverona where we lay our scene.
I mean, just right at the beginning of that,
two people, they're
very similar, but uh-oh,
stuff's about to happen.
It was the best of times, it was the worst
of times. You know, all these lines that
have become so classic because
after the fact, retrocessions,
respectively, we realize
that's the story in a nutshell.
But, you know, I search and search and
search and I throw them out, I start again,
I start somewhere else, and it's
all good, you know, it's all
discovery. The
overstory line,
first there was nothing,
then there was everything.
I mean, if you're not
sympathetic, you could say
that's kind of
philosophical mumbo jumbo.
And, you know,
the Gospel of John works a little bit like that.
It could be a little bit of a mystification,
you know. What in the beginning was the
Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God.
Yeah. And these sort of
linguistic
play with the
metaphysics of what's being expressed.
Well, that line actually
comes from
one of the last
sentences
that a dear
friend of mine and a brilliant American
poet said on her deathbed.
And as she was drifting
in and out of consciousness,
and, you know,
her loved ones were standing by, and she
would talk, and they would lean in, and
what is she saying? You know,
she said something, they couldn't
hear her, and they leaned in, she
said, first there was nothing.
Then there was
everything.
And I thought, you know, what a better
way to memorialize the life and work
of this friend than to take that
and promote it to the start of this book.
If I remember
correctly, you
wanted to be a poet,
or you were very interested in poetry early on? I still want to be a poet.
You still want to be a poet. When I grow up,
yeah, I may end up that way.
I don't know. Yeah.
But that's
that's the place
where those of us
who love language first
can focus
on that as the primary
pursuit. And there's also drama in
poetry. There's voice, and there's characterization.
There's structure, for sure, and form. We didn't even get
to how drama
generates form and structure.
But in poetry, you see,
most of your job
is to create
visceral
sensations
through the musicality of your words.
I mean, there's
there are a lot of other jobs that poets do, and
of course, poetry itself is a moving
target, and historically has been interested
in different things at different times, and
you know, what's considered the
central preoccupation of poetry has changed
so much, even in the course of my lifetime.
But how does drama create form?
Yeah.
So, we've seen these three kinds of collisions.
And in
any collision, what you're
talking about, the primary variable,
is tension.
In a collision, you go from a
low tension state to a high tension state.
Right?
And then,
you can relax that tension
as the drama is resolved. And then
it starts up again somewhere else, and the tension goes.
So, you are dialing in and out
of something that most
of us can read
intuitively as
the stakes. Right?
And what we call
tension is the realization on the part
of the protagonists that the stakes
are going up.
Now, when you think
of form
as trying to address
the potentials and the problems
of tension, now you're
thinking, what does
a writer want to do from
page one to page four hundred
to manipulate the
tension in the reader?
And of course, it's going
up and down all the time, depending on the drama
of individual scenes.
But we have
the ability to tell
stories, you know, this
weird adaptation that the human brain
has for imagining
creating imaginary spaces
and saying, you know, what if
this guy
said this to this guy?
Right? We
know that when we tell even the simplest
stories, there's a
kind of structure that makes
sense with regard to tension,
and there's a kind of structure that doesn't
make sense. If I said
once upon a
time, there was a prince,
and the prince
wrote out on his
steed, and he
killed the most
challenging dragon in the country.
And then, the next
year, the prince rode out on his horse,
and he killed
a dragon that was somewhat
challenging. Right.
That wouldn't make any sense.
You know, the finale
being, and then he killed the easiest
dragon in the country. It would never work like that.
Makes no sense at all. So we have
an intrinsic, which would
actually, it would merit some
investigation as to
why that makes
absolute sense to us
to stack tension as a rising
thing. You know,
to think about that as a
physiological thing, as
part of this,
you know,
adaptive power that we have
to intrigue other people with story.
But a
simple rising
action isn't
really the most satisfying kind of
story anyway, especially for
long form, right?
So, you know,
you have to sculpt
that tension graph
in a way that
does justice to your characters,
does justice to your readers'
expectations, and keeps your readers
intrigued. Because, you know,
there's a certain
kind of tension in just
wanting to know what happens next.
There's a certain kind of tension
in knowing that there are mysteries early
on in a story that you can't explain.
And so there's that
reverse anticipation of
knowing that
eventually you're going to get an
explanation of something that right now
is completely mysterious to you.
So I would teach the tension
graph as having
four parts.
A hook
where at the beginning tension
is just a little bit higher,
artificially higher, right?
In order to say
here's what's,
this is going to draw you into this world.
There's some stakes early on that you're
going to immediately be viscerally interested in.
And once you
get the reader hooked
with that higher level of
tension, you can relax
the tension a little bit as you move into
what I would call the exposition.
Who's who? Who are
they?
What is the
crisis? What is the
stakes? Where are these
people coming from? Getting everybody
on stage.
You've earned the
ability to relax the tension
and get everybody on stage
because you've had that little bit of a
bait and switch.
Once
the reader is oriented
in this world, once a certain
amount of things have been exposed,
shown to be,
then you can start to explore
the instabilities of those people
in that situation.
Now we go back to drama and
every value
creates an unstable counter value
and every
contact with another human being
creates an instability in what
those people want and need.
Now you go through
the great middle part of the book
which is the rising action.
The stakes get higher.
Every time something gets
solved, it produces a larger instability
because the ramifications
of solving that
first little episode
are larger than the first episode
itself. So you go up
this ladder and you eventually
reach, you can't,
you hit the wall. You can't
raise the stakes any farther. You've reached
the ultimate dramatic conflict.
That's the climax
of the book.
Now typically, we
don't save that for the last page of the book.
We have this
follow on that says
okay, now that you've
seen the final jumps
that everybody's made,
now that you've seen what everybody has
chosen as their core inner
value and seen the way that they
have to now live with the consequences
of their choices,
you release that back into the world.
We use a French word for this in
narratology, the denouement,
which we think of as
the revelation or the
consequences.
But it literally means the
tying. So you've been wrenching
the knot tighter and tighter and tighter. You
get to the climax, it blows apart. And now
what happens in the world
suggests anyway the trajectory
of these people who have gone
through fire and now
are different than they were before.
In what ways are they different? In what ways
will the world that they live in be different?
We need enough of that to know what the
final consequences of that climax
would be. Have you
picked up any similar tools
for writing dialogue? Because dialogue
is a representation
of how people actually speak, but it
isn't, it's far more efficient,
dare I say, than actual human
conversation. It's highly stylized.
I mean, if you were to sit on the
back of a bus here in the city
and just transcribe the way that people
talk to each other and try to pass that off on the
page, you could make the claim,
this is the most realistic dialogue you'll ever
hear. It'd be terrible. It would be
chaotic
and incoherent and, you know,
that we
depend on certain conventions
and
by when we say real
or vivid, we're
not actually talking about
empirically
accurate. We're talking about
the recognition of certain
narrative expectations
that we've learned from
the kinds of fiction that are viable
in our culture right now.
Conventional dialogue, realistic
dialogue, is the dialogue
that knows how to manipulate the
conventional expectations
that have been established for dialogue
at this moment. And
you don't have to go back
very far
to start leaving
your comfort zone
in dialogue.
If you're every day, if you're
cutting your IT and you're just living on
fiction that's been written in the
last ten years and you're shaping your
ear on those conventions
and you go back 20 years or 40
years or 100 years,
you might say,
people don't talk like
that. But all you're
saying is, I've lost my
context, my
decoder ring for
understanding how
these dialogues were. So when you're
writing, what are you doing to
make it
feel alive
without it feeling,
like you said, empirically accurate
to how people speak? I think you have to hear it
out loud because I think that's the way that
most readers
are actually going to consume
the narrative.
When we read, we sub-vocalize.
You're hearing it
sub-vocally.
And that's why sometimes
for authors, it's tough
to listen to their own audiobooks
because
they've just spent a couple of years
sub-vocalizing all these characters
and now they have to hear these
characters literalized by some other
voice actor. And they're going, no,
no, no, that's not what I'm hearing in my head.
You know.
But to create
dialogue that
can elicit different kinds of emotions
from people
is always
furthered, I think,
by actually saying it out loud.
And, you know,
testing it in the
crucible of your ear.
Right? So that
when your readers do the same
thing, you at least have a little
sense of
the register, the tone,
the color, the cadence,
the realism, the
socioeconomic accuracy
of that dialogue. I have no sense for this.
So, who is someone
who you really admire
with dialogue? And what
is it that you admire
about the way that they write it?
That you're trying to chase
or cultivate yourself?
There are practitioners that are
amazingly varied.
Like, you can get a writer like
Ann Patchett, who
whose characters
you even forget that they're
characters. You know, because
because she somehow can
participate in the way that they
speak so
vividly
and so virtuosically
that the
performance disappears entirely.
And you just say,
oh yeah, that's my
character. That's, you know,
the woman that I lived with for 11
years. You know, you're doing all
those things just through her ability
to let them speak themselves
to each other. But then you can also
get a writer who's aesthetically
completely different, like
Don DeLille. And you
can look at a book like White Noise
and you can look at the dialogue in that
book, which is crazy.
And highly
artificial in one
sense of the word artifice.
And yet you can say, this man
has the best ear
of any living writer because
he somehow can get to the absurdity
of the way that we talk
through each other, you know, or
uh
away from each other.
Yeah. You know, and it's
it's not realism.
It's, in some
ways it's kind of surreal what
he does with dialogue.
But it's so
real in
terms of recognizing
the crazy
way that we play this language game
with one another.
Okay, so what I want to do is I want to pop between some
different quotes. We'll kind of do a
fire round quote parkour. First one.
The best arguments in the world won't
change a single person's mind.
The only thing that can do that
is a good story.
I mean, in order to move somebody,
you have to use emotions.
Um,
and we
talked a great deal about
those two different appeals.
Uh, the appeal to logic
and reason and rationality and the appeal to
the guts. Yeah. Yeah.
If you would
learn the secrets of nature,
you must practice more humanity.
The secrets of nature are where
the secrets of humanity
arise.
We can see one another.
We can understand ourselves as
individuals
through the difference that we have
looking at another person.
But to understand what a human
being is,
we have to look at the more than human.
The loneliness
of writing is that you
baffle your friends and change
the lives of strangers.
I find this
true to the present day.
You know, I can
give the manuscript
to my
brother, and he can
return it a couple of weeks later
and say,
interesting.
And yet I can
turn my phone on this morning
and get an email
saying, you don't know me,
but
I'm studying forestry now
because of you.
You know, what sense does that make?
That's just crazy. Yeah.
When you're sure of what you're looking at,
look harder.
Yeah, because when you're sure,
you're not moving.
And reality is always moving.
Right?
If you've arrived
at a definitive, irrefutable
point of view,
it's because your point of view
is stationary.
And that's not going to help you survive
in a world where all points of view
are constantly moving.
Interesting. When I read that,
what I was thinking about was,
I was just thinking of the overstory, and I was thinking of,
the infinite number of things
that nature will reveal to you
if you sit and you stop
and you look and look and look.
Yeah. Attention is
the most profound source of meaning
that we can have.
And
before I wrote Overstory,
I had a path that I would walk
from my house to my office,
and it looked something like this.
Tree.
Tree. Tree.
And as I started
to write Overstory,
that path started to look like
this. Red oak.
Maple.
Uh, hornbeam.
Uh,
and then,
as I got deeper into
Overstory, it was,
oh, this guy.
You know, it's not a red oak,
it's this guy.
He's doing something that I've not seen
in the other red oaks in the neighborhood.
Right? So the
granularity, the particularity,
the pleasure of the world
depends on slowing
down and looking harder.
Yeah.
We have this sense that structure is
inimical to emotion.
Or that systems are inimical to
individuals. You know, that a book
can either be a heart book or a head book.
And my desire, of course,
is to write something that's like us.
Namely, an all-in-one.
And I like this idea
that you're getting at, which is
that there can be novels of thinking, novels of
feeling, novels of character, novels of
ideas, and
this is one of the
major themes of this conversation
is the fusion of
maybe even the right side and the left side of the
brain in the work that you're trying to do.
The sled is only
gonna move when all the dogs are
in harness and they're all pulling in the same direction.
But that's the craft
of writing, to find a way
in which all those different
approaches, and it's
far more than just head and heart. I mean,
there are 300 regions
of the brain, right?
So, what
you want to do is get all
the elements in your
repertoire
chosen in such a way that they're
supporting one another.
That the levels are emerging from the
decisions that you've made at the levels lower
down, and they're all in harness.
And in harmony.
I want to end by
hearing about some of the
time that you've spent writing in solitude.
You know, when you wrote Plowing in the
Dark, you said, I even wish that I
could have gone into a
sensory deprivation tank.
And it seems that
solitude has been
a major asset and strategy
over your career.
I agree with that,
but I think
I have to expand
the formulation just a little bit.
Moving in
and out of solitude
has been the strategy.
Huh. Right?
My composition process
and certain
amount of my revision
needs
to
remove the
overwhelming stimulus of the world
in order to be able to
create a richness
in my own imagination.
So, I write lying in bed.
I'll pull the covers up.
I'll dictate or I'll use a pen.
You know, I'll turn the light out
and do it in the dark.
I'll look up at the bare ceiling
as a way of
repurposing
all my sensory
apparatus that would ordinarily be taken
up with, you know,
the
amazing stimulus
of the world.
And now just going back
in tranquility and recollecting
places that I've been,
things that I've known,
crises that I've survived.
So, that requires solitude.
But if you stay
solitary,
you're gonna
spin out of orbit eventually.
Both literally and artistically.
Because
you won't have the world
to test the products of your
solitude against.
So you start to make a
character, you start to create a scene,
and you
need that sensory deprivation
to get going and to get
traction. But now
it's gained enough
complexity and momentum on its own.
What you want to know now is,
is it true? Does it
resonate? And to do
that, you gotta give up your solitude. You gotta
go back down into the maelstrom.
And I think so many
creators talk
about that. That
is a boundary condition.
You know, where you can control
both
the degree to which
you can isolate and organize
the complexities and the chaos of the
world, and
the degree to which you can plunge
back into the bracing,
rejuvenating, corrective
of a story
that you didn't tell.
Yeah. And you have to play the one off the other.
Well, it seems like you've really
experimented with different forms of composition.
Because you were just talking about
speech,
the typewriter or the keyboard,
there's handwriting.
How do you mix those and
how does
your language show up differently in
different input formats?
It's kind of scene dependent
and book dependent to some extent.
The ratio and
what I go to
at each moment.
It's also dependent on my
state of mind. But,
I mean, think of it the way that a musician
would use
different instruments.
You know, if you're writing a song,
you might reach for a guitar for a
certain kind of song. You might sit down at the
piano for a different kind of song.
Go out in the woods and
sing a cappella for
a new third kind of song.
Or you might
rotate.
You might try
different combinations in sequence or
in parallel.
I think the same for writing.
I think the tools that we use to write,
we reach for them when we need
them, when we detect
through our intuition
or through our intellect
that we need to slow down
or be more quiet or speed up,
be more lively.
And each
tool has its affordances and
allows you to get to different places.
Last question. Be
as concrete as possible with
your writing. How do you actually
think about your day-to-day structure
when you're writing in solitude? I mean, you were
talking about, I have this image of you just
pulling the covers over your head and being in there
and letting your imagination wander.
And do you set
deadlines for yourself?
How does that work? It's changed
enormously over my 40 years and 14
books. I
have always been a person
who's most alert in
the morning.
And, uh,
I always, uh,
for maybe the first 25,
30 years of my life, knew
that I was going to get best results
if I had
breakfast, if I minimized my interaction
with the world, resisted the attempt
to, you know, the, uh,
desire to read yesterday's
news or, you know,
to check my feeds,
and simply get to work
while
my brain was freshest.
And to, to stay
there until I had a thousand words,
that was the discipline.
That was what shaped the day.
I thought my job was
getting a thousand words out every day.
It worked
well for a long, long time.
Um, something
happened. I became a different kind of writer.
I can
point to the moment where it started, and I can point
to the moment where it started to accelerate.
But basically,
I now no longer see
my day,
my primary job,
as getting a thousand words.
I see
my primary job
as being
in the world, the living
world. So the first
thing I will do in the morning is check
the weather report.
And the calendar.
And ask
myself, what's going on out there?
At what elevation?
And where's the show?
And where can I learn something?
And that's
my primary accountability now.
Uh, to see myself
through the non-human world,
to remember all of my experiences
of my life,
through having this extended final
chapter of meditation and presence.
And
usually, it means
that after a short time of being
quickened and revived by
uh, all these
amazements happening all around me,
without too much
deliberation, something that might have taken
me a lot of forced effort earlier
in my career,
sentences will start to come and
scenes will start to come.
And a lot of times, you know, I'll be four miles down
a trail and realize I gotta get
home as quickly as I can, cause I can't hold
it all in my memory anymore.
Uh, so, the
the writing now
is a supporting
process
for
trying to keep me
growing as a person in a
world that keeps growing.
That was such a fun
interview. Thank you so much for doing this.
Oh, my pleasure. It was great. It was great to meet you.
Thanks, David. Yeah. Yeah.